Guide to the Boswell Collection Supplement
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Boswell collection supplement
1750-1900
GEN MSS 153
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.25
(4 boxes)
The collection consists mainly of letters and writings by or pertaining to various members of the Boswell of Auchinleck family. Series III includes seventeen journals of weather conditions and work assignments on the Auchinleck estate.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
For more extensive holdings of Boswell family material, including the papers of James Boswell, see GEN MSS 89, Boswell Collection, and GEN MSS 150, Boswell Collection Addition.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to the Boswell of Auchinleck family, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to January 1995 have been organized into Series I, Letters, and Series II, Writings. Materials added to the collection since that time are located in Series II, Additions since July 1995, listed in the order in which they were added.
Boswell, Alexander, Sir, 1775-1822; Boswell, Euphemia, 1774-1837; Boswell, James, Sir, 1807-1857; Boswell, James, 1740-1795; Boswell family
- Letters, Series I
  - BOSWELL, EUPHEMIA
    - Letters: to Mrs. Osbourne, [1836?]; 4 items. With 2 typescripts. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Scope and Contents
      4 ALS to Mrs. Osbourne, with whom Euphemia seems to have boarded, mentioning her illness and her financial difficulties.
      With: 2 typescripts carbon of "Ballad, Written in 1817, by Euphemia Boswell..."
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Purchased in 1995.
  - BOSWELL, JAMES, SIR, 1807-1857
    - Letter: 3 Melville Street [Edinburgh], to David Robertson, Esq, 1836 Jan 30; 1 item (2 leaves); 24 cm. With 1 typescript. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      ALS to David Robertson of Spottiswoode & Robertson, asking that he find lodgings for Euphemia Boswell.
- Writings, Series II
  - "Attention," manuscript, corrected, n.d.; 1 item (4 leaves); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Manuscript signed "Alex. Boswell" in unidentified hand.
    Purchased in 1993.
  - "The Brigs answer to John Gibson," holograph, corrected, n.d.; 1 item (4 leaves); 30.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Crazy Paul's Flight to Pandemonium," manuscript, 1 item (2 leaves); 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Pencil note under title: "by Alex Boswell."
  - "Solitude," manuscript, n.d.; 1 item (1 leaf); 23 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Docketed "Solitude a poem by Alexr. Boswell Esqr."
  - "The Woo Creel, or the Bill o'Bashan," holograph, corrected and annotated, [ca. 1816?]; 1 item (4 leaves); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Incomplete: missing last 18 lines.
- Additions Since July 1995, Series III
  - Contract between John Murray and John William Croker: "Assignment of the copyright of the work called Boswell and additions by John William Croker", 1 item (2 leaves); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8a)
    With: "Macaulay and Croker: Croker's Edition of Boswell's Johnson, 1831.
    Macaulay's Review of the Same." Printed. [ca. 1882]
    "Answers to Mr. Macaulay's Review" Printed. 1856
    Newspaper clipping from The Standard ,"Skye" 1872 Oct 9
    Printed sheet concerning The Club n.d.
    Purchased in 1997.
  - GIFT OF HALSTED B. VANDERPOEL, YALE 1935S
    - James Boswell Letters to Andrew Gibb
      - Letter: London, 1781 Jan 11 (Box 4, Folder 27)
        1 item (2 p.); 25 cm. x 19 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1790 Nov 8 (Box 4, Folder 28)
        1 item (1 p.); 23 cm. x 18 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1790 Dec 11 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Letter: London, 1790 Dec 16 (Box 4, Folder 30)
        1 item (4 p.) ;23 cm. x 19 cm. Concerning the power of factory Boswell is sending with this letter (not present); instructions about rent collection from various tenants. Repaired. Accompanied by: dealer catalog description.
      - Letter: London, 1790 Dec 25 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Letter: London, 1791 Feb 7 (Box 4, Folder 32)
        I item (1 p.); 25 cm. x 18 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1791 Feb 12 (Box 4, Folder 33)
        1 item (2 p.); 23 cm. x 18 cm. Concerning the imprisonment of Andrew Dalrymple for debt to Boswell; poultry sales.
      - Letter: London, 1791 Mar 11 (Box 4, Folder 34)
        1 item (2 p.) 23 cm. x 18 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1791 Mar 18 (Box 4, Folder 35)
        1 item (1 p.); 25 cm. x 18 cm. Concerning trees at Auchinleck.
      - Letter: London, 1791 Apr 2 (Box 4, Folder 36)
        1 item (2 p.); 25 cm. x 18 cm. Concerning trees and repairs.
      - Letter: London, 1791 May 10 (Box 4, Folder 37)
        1 item (2 p.); 20 cm. x 16 cm. Rents and finances.
      - Letter: London, 1791 Jun 10 (Box 4, Folder 38)
        1 item (2 p.); 20 cm. x 16 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1791 Jun 29 (Box 4, Folder 39)
        1 item (2 p.); 23 cm. x 16 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1791 Jul 6 (Box 4, Folder 40)
        1 item (2 p.) 23 cm. x 18 cm. Expects to arrive at Auchinleck August 10. AN on last leaf: "8 July. I could not get a frank until to-day."
      - Letter: London, 1791 Aug 1 (Box 4, Folder 41)
        1 item (2 p.); 23 cm. x 18 cm. Expects to arrive at Auchinleck about August 25. Accompanied by: catalog description.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Feb 10 (Box 4, Folder 42)
        1 item (1 p.); 23 cm. x 18 cm. Concerning farm tenants.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Mar 26 (Box 4, Folder 43)
        1 item (2 p.); 20 cm. x 16 cm. Concerning the "Account of Improvements" for 1791.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Apr 2 (Box 4, Folder 44)
        1 item (1 p.); 22 cm. x 18 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Jun 9 (Box 4, Folder 45)
        1 item (1 p.); 23 cm. x 18 cm. Accompanied by: catalog description.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Jun 15 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Letter: Chelmsford, 1792 Oct 2 (Box 4, Folder 47)
        1 item (2 p.); 23 cm. x 18 cm. Boswell in Chelmsford on business; gives direction concerning rents.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Oct 12 (Box 4, Folder 48)
        1 item (1 p.); 34 cm. x 20 cm. Concerning rent for various properties, including Dalblair and Drumfork. Mentions Mr. Dun's illness. Accompanied by: typed transcript and catalog description.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Oct 29 (Box 4, Folder 49)
        1 item (2 p.); 20 cm. x 17 cm. Various farm rentals
      - Letter: London, 1792 Nov 13 (Box 4, Folder 50)
        1 item (3 p.); 26 cm. x 19 cm. Concerning various farm rentals and the selection of a new minister for the parish; requests butter for his brother and honey for himself.
      - Letter: London, 1792 Nov 29 (Box 4, Folder 51)
        1 item (2 p.); 20 cm. x 18 cm. Raising the price of coal by a halfpenny per creel.
      - Letter: London, 1793 Jan 24 (Box 4, Folder 52)
        1 item (2 p.); 23 cm. x 18 cm. Concerning estate business; the appointments of a postmaster a replacement for Mr. Dun. Accompanied by: typed transcript, carbon.
      - Letter: Glasgow, 1793 Mar 23 (Box 4, Folder 53)
        1 item (4 p.); 25 cm. x 19 cm. Concerning the rental of Braehead and plantings of trees. Lists of tenants in pencil in hand of Andrew Gibbs (?).
      - Letter: London, 1793 Jul 10 (Box 4, Folder 54)
        1 item (1 p.); 23 cm. x 19 cm. Concerning the dinner for the new minister's ordination, and refusing a contribution to a fund for seamen. Accompanied by: catalog description and bill of sale (1957 Apr 25)
      - Letter: London, 1793 Aug 13 (Box 4, Folder 55)
        1 item (2 p.); 32 cm. x 20 cm. Concerning tenants who have failed to pay rents. Accompanied by: typed transcript.
      - Letter: London, 1793 Dec 13 (Box 4, Folder 56)
        1 item (4 p.); 21 cm. x 17 cm. Concerning Knockroon; road repair; payments to be disbursed in January. Annotated in pencil, "Tinker #16."
      - Letter: London, 1793 Dec 19 (Box 4, Folder 57)
        1 item (2 p.); 32 cm. x 20 cm. Boswell's displeasure with several tenants; requests accounts for 1793 be drawn up promptly. Accompanied by: catalog description.
      - Letter: London, 1794 Feb 24 (Box 4, Folder 58)
        1 item (2 p.); 20 cm. x 17 cm. Requests copies of accounts for 1793.
      - Letter: London, 1794 Mar 27 (Box 4, Folder 59)
        1 item (4 p.); 20 cm. x 17 cm. Concerning measures to be taken with tenants in arrears; other estate business; requests copies of accounts for 1793. Accompanied by: typed transcript.
      - Letter: London, 1794 Apr 3 (Box 4, Folder 60)
        1 item (1 p.); 23 cm. x 19 cm.
      - Letter: London, 1794 May 1 (Box 4, Folder 61)
        1 item (2 p.); 21 cm. x 17 cm. Concerning tenants in arrears who are to be poinded.
      - Bibliographical information, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - OVERSIZE MATERIAL
    - Journals for the estate of Auchinleck, 1772-81; 10 items. (Box 2, Folder 9-18)
      The journals record the daily weather, including barometer readings for some years, and details of work done by tradesmen and laborers on the estate.
      In blue paper wrappers
      Purchased in 1996.
    - Journals for the estate of Auchinleck, 1784-90; 7 items. (Box 3, Folder 19-26)
      The journals record the daily weather, including barometer readings for some years. Those for 1784-86 also give details of work done by tradesmen and laborers on the estate.
      In blue paper wrappers.